Finding Aid for William K. Anderson Papers 1878-1967
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William K. Anderson Papers 1878-1967, 1936-1964
Anderson, William K., 1896-1967.
1 oversize volumes
3 linear feet
Detroit, Michigan, businessman, founder of Detroit Power Squadron and officer with its parent body, the United States Power Squadrons. Series in the collection include United States Power Squadrons; Boating Organizations; Published and unpublished articles and speeches; World War II Activities; Personal and Miscellaneous; and Photographs.
85653 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was the gift of Anderson's daughter, Catherine Baker (donor no. 4044 ) and came to the library in 1968.
The collection is open for research.
William K. Anderson was born in 1896 in Thompsonville, Benzie County, Michigan. Following his graduation from Sparta High School in 1915, he entered the University of Michigan to study marine engineering. Soon after war was declared in 1917, Anderson joined up with the Michigan Naval Militia which had been organized at the University of Michigan in 1916. During the war, Anderson served as Quartermaster 1st class and CQM-Acting, and saw duty on gunboats, subchasers, destroyers, and transports. For some of this time, he was stationed at Queenstown, Ireland.
After the war, Anderson continued his engineering education at the Amour Institute of Technology in Chicago (1922-1923) and then at Cleveland College (1925-1926). For a time thereafter, he worked with Western Electric Company and then as an independent machine design engineer at Motor Testing Equipment,Inc. From 1932 and for the rest of his life, Anderson was a self-employed design engineer. One of his firms engaged in designing and supervising the building of test equipment for automobile factories and service stations. Through another company, he distributed, installed, and serviced radio telephones and direction finders for vessels on the Great Lakes.
Although a man of many interests, Anderson's devoted his lifework to his love of boating and the appropriate regulation of the waters of the Great Lakes. In 1936, he reactivated the Detroit Power Squadron as a local unit of the United States Power Squadrons (USPS). The USPS had been established before the First World War by Assistant Secretary of the Navy Franklin Roosevelt who saw the need for an organization to provide operational and training support for the Navy. Its objectives were to establish a high standard of skill in the handling and navigation of yachts, to encourage the study of navigation and small boat handling, and to otherwise provide activities which would strengthen the nation's military services. As head of the Detroit Power Squadron, Anderson worked to expand the principles of the USPS to the Great Lakes. From 1936 to 1938, in addition to his work with the Detroit unit, Anderson served as secretary of the USPS. In 1938 he was appointed rear commander of the organization, vice commander in 1939, and chief commander in 1941.
After the beginning of World War II, Anderson volunteered to join the U.S. Navy. He was appointed Lt. Commander and served at Norfolk Naval Air Station as ships service officer. He stayed in that position for two years before he was transferred to Tacoma, Washington as navigating officer for different aircraft carriers. Anderson was released from the Navy in 1944 and went back to Detroit, where he continued his active involvement in boating and boating education. In 1946 as executive secretary, he brought the headquarters of the American Power Boat Association to Detroit.
Anderson was also active in promoting legislation affecting the nation's waterways, in particular the waters of the Great Lakes. On the national scene, he argued for the establishment of marine highways and harbors of refuge. In Michigan, he was partially responsible for the establishment in 1947 of the Michigan Waterways Commission. After its creation, he fought long and hard to advance the proposition that taxes spent by the state's boatmen for gasoline fuel should be given over to the Waterways Commission for projects of benefit to them.
He also made many public speeches each year and was a prolific writer mainly on topics relating to boating, navigation history, and naval history. William K. Anderson died in 1967.
The papers of William K. Anderson consist primarily of materials relating to his life-long interest in boating, navigation, and other marine activities. Most heavily documented are those files detailing his involvement with various powerboat groups, the United States Power Squadrons and the Detroit Power Squadron being the most prominent. The collection has been divided into six series: United States Power Squadrons, Boating Organizations, Writings, World War II Activities, Miscellaneous and Personal, and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Power Boat Association.; Anderson, William K. (William Knowlton), 1896-1967.; Boats and boating--Michigan.; Detroit River (Mich. and Ont.); Detroit Yacht Club.; Great Lakes.; Harbors of refuge--Michigan.; United States. Naval Reserve.; United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve.; United States. Navy.; United States Power Squadrons.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.; Yachting--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Anderson, William K. (William Knowlton), 1896-1967.; Fremont (Mich.); Interiors--Business enterprises.; Lake County (Mich.); Michigan--Naval militia.; Michigan--Naval militia.; Millstones.; Thompsonville (Mich.)
Contributors:
Anderson, William Albert, 1840-1903.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Tintypes.
- United States Power Squadrons 1918, 1936-1956
  The United States Power Squadrons series (1918 and 1936-1965; 1 linear feet) documents Anderson's involvement as officer with the USPS and with the Detroit Power Squadron. Topics covered relate to the education of boatmen, the development of the organization as an effective vehicle for publicizing the needs of boatmen, and the expansion of the USPS to different sites.
  - Appointment Committee 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Coast Guard October 1940-January 1941, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Committee on Advanced Grades 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Rules 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Power Squadron
    - Constitution and bylaws 1936 (Box 1)
    - General correspondence 1936-1939, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    - Report of meeting March 1, 1918 (Box 1)
    - Rosters, newsletters, and other publications 1930s-1950s (Box 1)
  - Expansion Committee December 1938-November 1939, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Legislative concerns (marine fuel tax, boat tax, boating safety, etc.) 1949-1956 (Box 1)
  - Minutes and memoranda 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (include course materials), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Navigation course materials 1938 (Box 1)
  - Publications (Box 1)
  - Put-in-Bay (re installation of an aid to navigation light) December 1938-April 1939 (Box 1)
  - Rear Commander's file January-December 1938, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Vice Commander's file January-November 1939, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Boating Organizations 1938-1965
  The Boating Organizations series (1938-1965; 0.25 linear feet) documents Anderson's involvement with other boating groups and his concern with matters relating to boating. Among the organizations represented in this series are the American Power Boat Association, the Detroit River Yachting Association, and the Detroit Yacht Club.
  - American Power Boat Association December 1944-December 1947 (Box 2)
  - Detroit River Yachting Association April 1945-August 1945 (Box 2)
  - Detroit Yacht Club
    - Correspondence August 1957-April 1965 (Box 2)
    - Various, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (include annual reports, bulletins, minutes, etc.)
    - Patrol Committee (for regatta) May 1938-June 1939 (Box 2)
- Writings
  The Writings series (0.25 linear feet) includes both published and unpublished writings of Anderson. There are also speeches and conferences papers. Anderson was interested in all facets of Great Lakes history, and among his writings is a lengthy geological history of the Detroit River and a folder relating to the defense of the Great Lakes during wartime.
  - Defense of the Great Lakes (writings about) (Box 2)
  - Geological history of the Detroit River; How nature created the Detroit River; L'Histoire du d'Etroit (Story of the Narrows); etc (Box 2)
  - Published writings (Box 2)
  - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Various, 3 folders (Box 2)
- World War II Activities 1940-1945
  World War II Activities (1940-1945; 0.5 linear feet) details Anderson's military service. Although the official papers within the series (orders, requisitions, etc.) are fairly routine, the highlight of this series are those scores of letters that Anderson exchanged with his wife, Mildred Anderson while serving in the Navy.
  - Correspondence with wife, Mildred Anderson June 1941-February 1944, 11 folders (Box 2)
  - Navy Department (correspondence with and related materials) 1940-1945, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous personal correspondence (Box 2)
  - Ships' histories for USS Wake Island and USS Kitkun Bay (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous and Personal 1878-1902, 1933-1966
  Miscellaneous and Personal (1878-1902 and 1933-1966; 0.7 linear feet) includes scattered business records of his father William A. Anderson, newspaper clippings and a scrapbook relating to Anderson's activities with the USPS, and files relating to Detroit neighborhood politics. After World War II, Anderson and his wife took an extended trip using inland waterways beginning in Detroit, going as far south as Florida, then back to Detroit using waterways along the eastern seaboard. This series includes his narrative account of that voyage as well as a scrapbook of photographs, postcards and clippings relating to the trip. Anderson's daughter Catherine was a member of the WAVES during World War II, and her letters with her father provide information on the role of women in the military services.
  - Anderson, William A. (father)
    - Correspondence 1878-1902 (Box 3)
    - Business records 1879-1902 (Box 3)
  - Anderson, Catherine 1943-1944 (Box 3)
    (letters with father regarding service with WAVES; also include some Mae Ora letters to WKA)
  - Biographical material (Box 3)
  - Business records (William K. Anderson, Inc.) 1933-1954 (Box 3)
  - Civil defense 1952-1963 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 3)
  - Detroit Waterfront Planning Committee April 1945-June 1945 (Box 3)
  - Genealogical materials (Box 3)
  - Jefferson-Chalmers Community Council 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Marine radio December 1939-June 1946 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Planning Commission Advisory Committee on Harbors of Refuge Programs (and related harbor of refuge materials) 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings mainly relating to yachting regattas and World War II activities 1936-1966, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings with references to WKA 1935-1941 also articles by WKA (Volume 1)
  - South Lakewood Area Association 1963 (Box 3)
  - Voyage from Detroit to Detroit (via the Mississippi River, across to Florida, up the coast using inland waterways, etc.)
    - Narrative entitled "A Little Trip Around the Island" (also lengthy letters home) 1945-1946 (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook 1945-1946 containing photographs, postcards, and clippings relating to southern cruise of Le Voyageur (Box 3)
  - Water diversion 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - Yachting miscellanea (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The last series, Photographs, consists of three folders of collected family and personal photographs. There are tintypes of his father and grandfather, and also photographs of his Sparta High School class (1915).
  - Sparta High School class album (and related) 1915 (Box 3)
  - Tintypes of family members (James Freeman Anderson and William Albert Anderson) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)